1.4 components of the PIMBOC guide.
Projects comprise several
key components that will
effectively manage result in
their successful completion.
This guide identifies and explains these
components.
The various components interrelate to each
other during the management of a project.
The key components are described briefly
in Table 13.
These components are more fully explained
in the sections that follow the table.
Please pay particular attention to this
diagram because you can see that the first
entry mentions a series
of phases that the project
passes through and the
second mentions project phases.
However, the phases that
the project passes through
and project phases are
two quite different things.
They're not related despite the name.
This catches a lot of people on the exam.
The series of phases should really be
called the series of stages or similar
because it means, for example, initiation
phase, planning phase and so on.
But a project phase is more like a mini
project within the main project.
For example, if you are managing a project
to build an office block, you might have a
separate project phase to do the
landscaping.
It's within the main project, but managed
as a separate project.
Component one of the PIMBOC guide is the
project lifecycle.
A project life cycle is
the series of phases that a
project passes through
from its start to its completion.
You need to know that for the examination.
It provides the basic framework for
managing the project.
This basic framework applies regardless of
the specific project work involved.
The phases may be sequential, iterative,
i.e.
you do them over and over
again, or overlapping, you may
do two at the same time,
two or more at the same time.
All projects can be mapped to the generic
lifecycle shown in figure 1,5,
and please note that this generic life
cycle appears on the exam now and then,
so you need to memorize that.
It's quite a simple thing to learn.
And along on this diagram, it's quite hard
to see the forest for the trees.
The generic lifecycle is up at the top of
the diagram.
And you can see it's one starting the
project, two, organizing and preparing,
three, carrying out the work for end in
the project.
And in this section on life cycles,
when you see the word phase, think of a
stage such as those in the generic life
cycle.
Development life cycles can be predictive,
iterative, incremental,
adaptive or a hybrid model.
What does that mean?
In a predictive life cycle,
the project scope, time and
cost are determined in the
early phases of the life cycle.
The word predictive means being able to
predict or to see ahead because you're
trying to predict everything in detail
right from the start of the project,
which is the time.
When you know the least about it,
it's also referred to as a waterfall life
cycle because it's like walking down a
flight of stairs, but you can't go back up
the stairs again, and so it's like taking
a canoe over a series of waterfalls.
In an iterative life cycle, the project
scope is generally determined early in the
project life cycle, but time and cost
estimates are routinely modified as the
project team's understanding of the
product increases.
Iterations develop the project through a
series of repeated cycles, while
increments successfully add to the
functionality of the product.
And so here you are acknowledging that
trying to predict everything in detail
right from the start of the project,
where you know the least about it,
is probably not the best way to do it.
And so in an iterative life cycle,
you're treating the project more like an
experiment, which in many
cases, especially in information
technology projects,
that's exactly what it is.
In an incremental lifecycle, the
deliverable is produced through a series
of iterations that successfully add
functionality within a predetermined timeframe.
The deliverable contains a
necessary and sufficient capability
to be considered complete
only after the final iteration.
This one reminds me of the old riddle.
How can you eat a whole elephant?
Answer, one bite at a time.
Adaptive life cycles are agile,
iterative or incremental.
The detail scope is defined and approved
before the start of one iteration.
Adaptive life cycles are also referred to
as agile or change-driven life cycles.
This type of life cycle is fast moving and
though it's far removed from the
waterfall, say when you're managing an
adaptive life cycle, project, it can feel
like you're in that little canoe
plummeting over a waterfall.
A hybrid life cycle is a combination of
predictive and adaptive life cycle.
These elements of the project
that are well known or have
fixed requirements for a
predictive development life cycle.
And those elements that are still evolving
follow an adaptive development lifecycle.
It's up to the project management
team, not just the Project
Manager to determine the
best lifecycle for each project.
The project life-cycle needs
to be flexible enough to
deal with the variety of
factors included in the project.
Life cycle flexibility may be accomplished
by identifying the process or processes
needed to be performed in each phase,
performing the process or processes
identified in the appropriate phase,
adjusting the various attributes of a
phase, the example name, duration,
exit criteria and entrance criteria.
Project life cycles are
independent of product
life cycles which may
be produced by a project.
A product life cycle is a series of phases
that represent the evolution of the
product from concept
through delivery, growth,
maturity and to its eventual
end of life or retirement.
For example, a project lifecycle,
to develop the first Concord supersonic
aircraft took about eight years, but the
product life cycle was about 46 years.
That's eight years of development,
plus 38 years until retired from service.
However, I noticed recently that one
Concord has been bought by a group of
businessmen, we're hoping to put it back
into service, so the product life cycle
might end up a lot longer than the 46
years.
Project phase.
The Pimbook guide says a project phase is
a collection of logically related project
activities that culminates in the
completion of one or more deliverables.
The phases in a life cycle can be
described by a variety of attributes.
Attributes may be measurable and unique to
a specific phase.
Attributes may include the name of For
example, phase A, phase B, phase one,
phase two, proposal phase.
Numbering, e.g., three phases in the
project, five phases in the project.
Duration, example, one week, one month,
one quarter.
Resource requirements, e.g., people,
buildings, equipment.
Entrance criteria for a project to move
into that phase, e.g., specified
approvals, documents, specified
documents complete, and
exit criteria for a project
to complete a phase, e.g.
documented approvals, completed documents,
completed deliverables.
Projects may be separated into distinct
phases or sub-components.
These phases or
sub-components are generally given
names that indicate the type
of work done in that phase.
You can find a list of typical phase names
on page 20 of the PIMBOC guide,
but they could include names such as
build, test transition etc decision points
example funding project go-no-go and
milestone review number three phase gate
this is where you check the project
performance at the end of a phase and
management decides if the projects should
continue you can read more about this on
page 21 of the PIMBOC guide four project
management processes the project life
cycles manage is managed
by executing a series of project
management activities known
as project management processes.
Every project management process produces
one or more outputs from one or more
inputs by using appropriate project
management tools and techniques and you
will find that we'll actually spending
most of the rest of this course on
processes with their inputs, tools and
techniques and outputs.
The output can be a deliverable or an
outcome.
Outcomes are an end result of a process.
Project management processes apply
globally across industries.
Project management processes are logically
linked by the outputs they produce.
Processes may contain overlapping activities
that occur throughout the project.
The output of one process generally
results in either an input to another
process or a deliverable of the project or
project phase.
The number of process
iterations and interactions between
processes varies based
on the needs of the project.
Processes generally fall into one of three
categories.
Processes used once or at predetermined
points in the project, the processes
develop project charter and closed project
or phase are good examples of that.
Processes that are performed periodically
as needed.
The processes acquire resources is
performed as resources are needed.
The process conduct procurements is
performed prior to needing the procured item.
Processes that are performed continually
throughout the project.
The process define activity may occur
throughout the project lifecycle,
especially if the project uses rolling
wave planning or an adaptive development
approach, many of the monitoring and
controlling processes are ongoing from the
start of the project until it is closed
out.
Project management is accomplished to the
appropriate application and integration of
logically group project management
processes.
While there are different ways of grouping
processes, the pinball guide groups
processes into five categories called
process groups.
Okay, starting with project management
process group, it's largely grouping of
project management processes to achieve
specific project objectives.
Process groups are independent of project
phases.
Project management
processes are grouped into the
following five project
management business groups.
Initiating process group, those processes
perform to define a new project or a new
phase of an existing project by obtaining
authorization to start
the projecter phase.
Planning process group, the process is
required to establish the scope of the
project, refine the objectives and define
the course of action required to attain
the objectives that the project was
undertaken to achieve.
Executing process group, those processes
perform to complete the work defined in
the project management plan to satisfy
project requirements.
And just a reminder, as I've said a couple
of times so far, and we'll cover more
detail later, the project plan is not the
project schedule.
A project plan is a collection of 18 plans
which includes the project schedule.
Monitoring and controlling process group.
Those processes require
to track, review and
regulate the progress and
performance of the project.
Identify any areas in which
changes to the plan are
required and initiate the
corresponding changes.
Closing process group, those processes
perform to formally complete or close the
project, phase or contract
and all those definitions for
the five process groups are
important for the examination.
Process flow diagrams are used throughout
the guide.
The project management processes are
linked by specific inputs and outputs
where the result of or outcome of one
process may become the input to another
process that is not necessarily in the
same process group.
Note that process groups are not the same
as project phases.
Number six, project management knowledge
areas.
In addition to the process groups,
processes are also categorised by
knowledge areas and it is
these knowledge areas that
we're going to spend most
of the time on the course.
and each one of the knowledge areas will
be divided into a number of processes.
You'll find this a
separate module for each
knowledge area, each
containing a set of lessons.
And I have aligned the numbering of the
modules and lessons with the PIMBOC guide
numbering to make it pretty easy to hop
between one and the other.
But something to be very wary of is that a
little of the knowledge areas appear in
sequence in the PIMBOC guide contents
page, which appears to be a logical
sequence, they are in fact used in almost
any order, they overlap, they're
interdependent and they may be repeated
many times.
Now let's look at the 10 knowledge areas
and I've included the PIMBOC definition of
each one as you'll
need to know these or at
least recognize these in the examination.
One project integration management
includes the processes and activities to
identify, define, combine, unify and
coordinate the various processes and
project management activities within the
project management process groups.
This is the knowledge area where the
project manager operates because the
project management role is integrative by
nature.
The remaining knowledge areas are the
domain of various specialist and technical
aspects, experts such as financial,
risk and scheduling experts, etc.
But project integration management is
centre stage for project manager.
Number two, project scope management
includes the processes required to ensure
the project includes all of
the work required and only
the work required to complete
the project successfully.
And that is one of the most common
definitions on the examination.
Number three, project schedule
management includes the processes
required to manage the
timely completion of the project.
This knowledge area has been renamed in
the sixth edition of the PIMBOR guide.
Previously, it was known as
project time management, but the
PMI Review Committee suggested
that time can't be changed.
It is only the processes that could be
changed inside the time because time
always progresses at a constant rate no
matter what you do.
Personally, I think this is changing words
just for the sake of changing words,
but you need to do it for the examination.
Number four, project cost management
includes the processes involved in
planning, estimating, budgeting,
financing, funding, managing and
controlling costs so the project can be
completed within the approved budget.
Number five, project quality management
includes the processes for incorporating
the organisation's quality policy
regarding planning, managing and
controlling project and
product quality requirements
in order to make stakeholder expectations.
I'm just reminding you these definitions
are all important for the examination.
Number six, project resource management
includes the processes to identify,
acquire and manage the resources needed
for a successful completion of the project.
This knowledge area changed with the sixth
edition of the Pumboch Guide.
It's not just the name change or big
changes into it.
Previously it was called Project Human
Resource Management but in this edition
has been expanded to include all physical
resources as well as the team resources.
Number seven project communications
management includes the process as
required to ensure timely and appropriate
planning, collection, creation,
distribution, storage, retrieval,
management, control, monitoring and
ultimate disposition of project
information.
Now I'm not sure about that word
disposition, maybe it means something
different in America than
from the rest of the world,
but that actually means the
disposal of the information.
It's quite often, business information has
to be kept by law, but usually it's
written in the law that after a certain
number of years that information could
then be disposed of or destroy the
information.
8 project risk management includes the
processes of conducting risk managing
planning, identification,
analysis, response planning,
response implementation
and monitoring risk on a project.
Knowledge area number 9 project
procurement management includes the
processes necessary to
purchase or acquire products,
services or results needed
from outside the project team.
Number 10, project stakeholder management
includes the processes required to
identify the people, groups or
organisations that could impact or be
impacted by the project to analyse
stakeholder expectations and their impact
on the project and to develop appropriate
management strategies to effectively
engage stakeholders in project management
decisions and execution.
Please study Table 1-4, which maps the
project.
management process groups and knowledge
errors and I mean study this in detail
many times it is really important it will
answer a lot of questions for you and will
answer a lot of questions on the
examination you'll find this in page 25 of
the PIMBOC guide and it brings us to the
end of components of the PIMBOC guide the
next module is tailoring please read the
corresponding chapter in the PINBOC guide
before watching the video so that you can
tailor your studies.